Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. We've got דף ה Daf Heh today,
probably one that we'll get through with a little ahead of time.
ס''ו, Samech Vav, we start with the next משנה, Mishna, and it's
continuing with the theme of how you פותח poteach for somebody, sort
of very good, obviously, for everybody, a person's נדר, neder, there will
be something that's very specific to the person, to his or her
circumstances and so on, which will afford a פתח. petach. But the
גמרא, Gemara, the משניות, Mishnayos, are talking about the
פותח poteach with suggestions or circumstances that are
pretty generic and that would allow many people to have a basis
for saying that had they thought about those circumstances, they would not
have wanted to do it. And part of the חידוש chiddush of
the משנה mishna in addition to giving advice is also to say
that going back to the debate about רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and
the חכמים chachamim about why you're פותח בכבוד אביו ואמו, poteach bichvod
aviv ve-imo, that these are not considered to be so universal that
we're afraid that people are going to lie—excuse
me, not lie—these are not considered so universal that we're afraid that
people are just going to figure, "Oh, I can
just get out of it myself," נדר Neder doesn't mean anything, it's
just so trivial because it always applies, that's one concern. But בכבוד
אביו ואמו bichvod aviv ve-imo the other concern is that nobody will
have been brazen enough to say, "I didn't care about that thing,"
right? So therefore people will lie in the process of it. So
those were the two concerns that came up with בכבוד אביו ואמו,
bichvod aviv ve-imo, so one can understand also that that's part of
the חידוש chiddush of the משניות mishnayos that we've read and will
be reading, that these types of things, while they're very, very general,
are not—we do not have a concern that they're so universal they'll
undercut the weight of the נדרים, nedarim, we don't have a concern
that they will have people give
untruthful responses. So let's take a look. פרק משנה ס''ו עמוד א.
Perek Mishna Samech Vav Amud Aleph. פותחין בימים טובים ובשבתות. Potchin beyomim
tovim u-vshabbatos.
You open up with the issue about יום טוב yom tov and
שבת. shabbos. Or somebody as we've seen in one, obviously it's a
standard נדר neder is about not benefiting from food, and you say
to the person, "Had you realized that that would get in the
way of you fully enjoying שבת shabbos and יום טוב, yom tov,
would you have made your נדר?" neder? You weren't thinking about the
fact that if you say, it's hard to say you weren't thinking
about the fact that שבת shabbos is that every week has a
שבת shabbos in it, but maybe some people that's not what's in
their mind when they're making the נדר neder or certainly that there's
a יום טוב yom tov coming up and so on, would you
have done it? And if he says no, then that's a basis
for allowing, and the ר''ן Ran also adds not just that you
make him think about how that would have made it hard for
him, but also you emphasize the fact that it would be a
lack of full fulfillment of his obligation. דאילו היה יודע שאסור להצטער
בשבת. De-ilu haya yode'a she-assur le-hitzta'er be-shabbos.
So again, bringing in the fact that it's wrong what you did,
and also the point a, that it'll hopefully encourage him to say
"I wouldn't have done it" if he thinks about that, but we're
also not afraid that it'll give a non-truthful response. Okay, so that,
now: בראשונה היו אומרים. Berishona hayu omrim. Now we get to a
very important הלכתי halakhic point. בראשונה היו אומרים אותן הימים מותרים ושאר
כל הימים אסורים. Berishona hayu omrim: otan hayamim mutarim, u-shear kol hayamim
assurim. As the person had said, "Yeah,
you're right, I wasn't thinking about שבת shabbos and יום טוב yom
tov when I said I wouldn't benefit from meat or wine or
something." Okay, then they used to say, "Okay, so now your נדר
neder doesn't apply to שבת shabbos and יום טוב," yom tov, meaning
we virtually reconstruct your נדר neder and we say, right,
had I been thinking about it I would not have said, I
would not have included שבת shabbos and יום טוב, yom tov, I
would have said meat and wine is אסור assur on me, on
all days except שבת shabbos and יום טוב. yom tov. So had
I been thinking about it. So do we say, "Okay, well then
that's what you deep down, we'll say that's what you part of
your נדר neder was בטעות, be-ta'us, the part that included שבת shabbos
and יום טוב, yom tov, and the rest of it wasn't בטעות
be-ta'us and we'll sort of virtually reconstruct a נדר neder or we'll
salvage the part that wasn't בטעות"? be-ta'us Or do we
say since it was בטעות... be-ta'us... Till עד שבא רבי עקיבא ולימד:
Ad she-ba Rabbi Akiva ve-limad: נדר שהותר מקצתו הותר כולו. neder she-hutar
miktzato hutar kullo.
There's two versions of this. One is maybe
an easier one: שהותר מקצתו הותר כולו. she-hutar miktzato hutar kullo. If
part of it what you were released from, you're released from all
of it. It's all one big unit. The other one's מכללו, miklalo,
meaning if something is excluded from the collective, from the totality, then
the whole thing is permissible. Is this still a נדר, neder, or
is it more like a שבועה? shevu'ah? Well,
נדר, neder, קונם הבשר עלי, konam ha-basar alai, except for שבת shabbos
or... Well, no, could be why? It still focuses on the
object, קונם בשר עלי, konam basar alai, during the weekdays.
So the same way you could say קונם בשר עלי כל שלשים
יום konam basar alai kol sheloshim yom or עד הפסח ad ha-Pesach
or whatever, right? You could sort of have it its status shift
on and off between the weekdays and שבת. shabbos. Now the ירושלמי,
Yerushalmi, the ר''ן Ran quotes the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, learns it out from
דכתיב, de-chtiv, the last four lines on the top, after the white
lines: ככל היוצא מפיו. ke-chol ha-yotzei mi-piv. ככל היוצא מפיו יעשה. Kichol
hayotzei mipi ya'aseh. גמרא שויא לה שקול
קיימא. Gemara shavya lah shakul kayama. It's all you have to do
everything. So if you release a guy from part of it, so
he's not obligated to do everything, he's not obligated to do everything,
he's not obligated to do to do anything. כיצד? Keitzad? So back
to the משנה. Mishna. And you're releasing him and interpreting, right? I
understand. כיצד, Keitzad, but that's whatever, that's why I said, that's why
it's a, oh, well back to interpreting we'll get, okay, hold on.
But here it's clear you meant the group, you weren't thinking about
שבת. Shabbos. But what if, let's take a look. What Michael I
think is getting at is exactly the next line of the משנה.
Mishna. כיצד. Keitzad. אמר, Amar, somebody said, קונם שאיני נהנה לכולכם. Konam
she'eini nehene l'kulchem. Actually, Michael, we'll just skip to the end of
this please, okay? I won't, you know, all of you
are forbidden from, you know, forbidden from deriving benefit from all of
you. הותר אחד מהן, Hutar echad meihen, and then you went through
a process of התרה, hatara, they said, had you realized that one
of the guys there was, I don't know, your next-door neighbor or
something, or was this, or was that, or had you thought about
the fact that you were, you know, invited over to his daughter's
wedding next week, you know, would you have made the נדר? neder?
Oh no, תקי, taki, I wasn't thinking about the fact that I
had to go to this guy's wedding next week. Okay, so now
you got out of it for that guy, so now it's הותר
לכולן, hutar l'kulan, because you made it all as a group. You
said I can't derive benefit from any of you. You went through
a process of התרה, hatara, you realized one of the guys hadn't
been thinking about it, you wouldn't have included him. So therefore it's
מותר mutar for
everybody. Okay, so הותר אחד מהן הותר לכולן. hutar echad meihen hutar
l'kulan. Now let's say you said שאיני או זהו, she'eini or zehu,
the question, שאיני שאני, she'eini she'ani, but anyway, שאיני נהנה לזה ולזה.
she'eini nehene la-zeh u'la-zeh.
So I'm not going to get benefit from
you or you or you or you or you or you, or
and, I don't know, it's a, ו' החיבור. Vav ha-hibbur. Yeah, so
we're going to get to that. So therefore, when I say לזה
ולזה ולזה ולזה ולזה ולזה ולזה, la-zeh u'la-zeh u'la-zeh u'la-zeh u'la-zeh u'la-zeh
u'la-zeh, it's
understood that what I am doing is saying a status that I've
now just assigned David over there, that he's forbidden, I'm forbidden to
derive benefit from him, that status also applies to Dov, and the
status that applies to Dov now also applies to Jonathan, and that
now also applies to Michael. So the status is being transferred and
it's being daisy-chained, essentially. And that's going to lead to the following
הלכה. halacha. Okay. הותר הראשון הותר כולן. Hutar harishon hutar kulan. So
if I figured out that, oh תקי, taki, I wasn't thinking about
the fact that they were going to come take some pictures for
me at my event next week or whatever, I wouldn't have included
him, right? So then everybody, then everybody is released because everybody's status
is based on his status. It's derivative of wherever it started. Exactly.
הותר האחרון, Hutar ha-acharon, if it's just Michael, you have four people,
then האחרון מותר וכולן אסורין. ha-acharon mutar v'kulan asurin. Everybody else remains
forbidden because I didn't say all of you as a unit. Is
this one נדר neder or four נדרים? nedarim? Right, that's the question.
So the two extremes is I said all of you, right? That's
a case where if I get released from one, I'm released from
all. The other extreme is I said נדר neder I won't be
benefit from you, נדר neder I won't benefit from you. Everyone is
a complete separate נדר. neder. Clearly, if you release from one, it
doesn't affect the other, so it's not one נדר. neder. This, one
minute, this is an interim case where it's effectively one נדר, neder,
so, but it's a, or but or a נדר neder which I
mean it might not even conceptually be a נדר, neder, but it's
a, it's just a ו' החיבור. Vav ha-hibbur. Maybe conceptually it is
a second נדר, neder, but it's a second נדר neder that builds
on the earlier one. Or it's one נדר neder that's structured in
a way, right, that the statuses are sort of building on each
other. So therefore, you know, it's possible to be released from part
and not released from the whole thing. Again, probably the conceptual model
here is that there're separate נדרים nedarim but they're building on the
previous ones. Okay. הותר האמצעי, Hutar ha-emtza'i, let's just read this line
and then I'll get to your question.
הותר האמצעי הימנו ולמטה מותרין הימנו ולמעלה אסורין. Hutar ha-emtza'i heimenu u'lemata
mutarin heimenu u'lemala asurin. So if the middle one, Dov, here I
got released from, so then I am free from everybody after Dov,
from Jonathan to Michael, but I am not free from David because
that was the, because everybody's after him status built on Dov, whereas
the person before him, the status is independent of Dov. Yes. Isn't
this the same concept with, with his father involved and whether in
the idea of whether the qualifier came at the beginning or at
the end? Good memory. So the גמרא Gemara quoted this מ"ח mem-chet
ago, about forty days ago, דף כ"ה, daf kaf-hei, and yeah, and
it sort of, the משנה Mishna and related things were brought into
that discussion. Yeah, so it's a good memory. And the גמרא Gemara
there tries to sort of reframe it in certain ways but we're
just now reading it. Whether the qualifier came at the beginning or
at the end. Exactly, exactly. To your earlier case where, you know,
each one is within the נדר, neder, right? קונם לזה ולזה. Konam
la-zeh u'la-zeh. Does that change it? No, well let's take a look.
Well so we'll see that in the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא's Gemara
going to discuss whether you needed the ו' vav or not. Okay.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Right,
but I think conceptually what we have to say here is that
we conceptualize these things as separate נדרים nedarim which are building on
one another, because if we conceptualized it as one big נדר, neder,
then it should follow the principle of הותר מקצתו הותר כולו, hutar
miktzato hutar kulo, right? So in a way this really isn't the
principle of הותר מקצתו הותר כולו, hutar miktzato hutar kulo, there's really
the principle of that they're separate נדרים nedarim but each one is
building on the earlier ones. Conceptually you'd have to say here because
if we conceptualized these things as separate נדרים nedarim which are building
on one another because if we conceptualized it as one big נדר
neder then it should follow the principle of הותר מקצתו הותר כולו
hutar miktzato hutar kulo right? So in a way this really isn't
the principle of הותר מקצתו הותר כולו hutar miktzato hutar kulo there's
really the principle of that they're separate נדרים nedarim but each second,
each following נדר neder is built on the previous one so therefore
it can have this ripple effect when you get released from one.
Now if somebody says שאני לזה she'ani l'zeh that's where they're built
on one another. If somebody says שאני נהנה לזה קורבן ולזה קורבן
she'ani neheneh lezeh korban ulezeh korban if you were to use the
word קורבן korban independently, if I say, you know, David is asur
to me קורבן korban or קונם, konam, you know, דוב Dov is
asur to me קונם, konam, יוסי Yosi is asur to me קונם,
konam,
so when I'm using the word קונם konam the magic word, I
think that's the technical magic word that identifies it as a נדר,
neder, right, but if I said David is asur to me נדר,
neder, דוב Dov is asur to me נדר, neder, what I'm basically
saying is that each one is independent. Okay, I have one נדר
neder for you, and one נדר neder for you, and one נדר
neder for you, and they're not linked to one another. Okay,
so in that case, צריכים פתח לכל אחד ואחד tzrichim petach lechol
echad ve'echad everything is an independent נדר. neder. קונם יין שאני טועם
שהיין רע למעי. konam yayin she'ani to'em shehayayin ra leme'ai.
So somebody says קונם konam wine I won't have is asur to
me because wine is bad for digestion. אמרו לו amru lo they
said to him והלא המיושן יפה למעי vehalo hameyushan yafeh leme'ai what
are you talking about? Old wine is very good for digestion. הותר
במיושן. hutar bameyushan.
So now he's no longer so now he's no longer forbidden on
old wine because it was clear he didn't want, you know, he
said it was only based on his assumption that wine was bad.
Right? I mean in a way actually this might not even be
היתר, heter, this might like be like a טעות, ta'ut, he had
a mistaken, you know, assumption or something, but anyway let's keep on
going.
הותר במיושן ולא במיושן בלבד הותר אלא בכל היין. hutar bameyushan velo
bameyushan bilvad hutar ela bechol hayayin. Right? Now this is very well
no this is tells you the logic of הותר מקצתו הותר כולו.
hutar miktzato hutar kulo. Okay?
You know had I known that had you know had I known
that that type of wine was good I never would've אסר asar'd
it. Okay? Now here's the question though: let's say he says yes
of course I knew that old wine was good for digestion I
was really only intending new wine you know new wine. So would
that be a case of הותר מקצתו hutar miktzato or would that
be a case where no where basically we at that time I
was aware of that fact and even though I just said generically
wine I really meant new wine, right? That would be a case
where I would say that the person that we would actually say
so we'll interpret the scope of what he said according to his
assumptions, right, and it wouldn't be a הותר מקצתו. hutar miktzato. When
he said wine he meant new wine. What did you think? I
said wine was bad for digestion, of course I meant new wine.
Right? So that's the case that that's not a case of הותר.
hutar. The case of הותר hutar seems to be a case where
I meant all wine, I didn't realize that new wine was good,
and therefore now part of my נדר neder was, you know, you
know in retrospect I wouldn't have wanted to include that in my
נדר neder but at the time I was intending to include it.
Does that mean he'd only
be אסור asur in new wine? What? He'd be אסור asur in
new wine. If that was right, if that's what he was thinking
at the time I think so. Okay so
now let's let's look at this next קונם בצל שאני טועם שהבצל
רע ללב. konam batzal she'ani to'em shehabatzal ra lalev. Let's say all
onions are forbidden שהבצל רע ללב shehabatzal ra lalev it's bad for
the heart.
אמרו לו והלא הכופרי יפה ללב amru lo vehalo hakufari yafeh lalev
but the
כופרי kufari onion is good for the heart. Oh I didn't know
that. הותר בכופרי. hutar bakufari. So now he's been released from the
כופרי. kufari. ולא בכופרי בלבד הותר אלא בכל הבצלים velo bakufari bilvad
hutar ela bechol habetzalim but all onions. מעשה היה והתיר רבי מאיר
בכל הבצלים. ma'aseh hayah vehitir Rabbi Meir bechol habetzalim. Rabbi Meir said
now you're allowed exactly a case like this. Again, but if the
guy says like, you know, no of course I didn't mean the
כופרי, kufari, of course you know I was only talking about like
the big onions like you know not this weird thing you get
at Whole Foods or something, I meant standard onions. You know? So
again that was what he was thinking at the time then I
assume that it wasn't wouldn't be a case of הותר, hutar, it
would just be a case
that its scope was interpreted by his דעת da'at at the time.
Yes tell me if this is not accurate. It sounds to me
that what the underlying this type of סוגיא sugya is that it's
completely within the discretion of the בית דין beit din or of
the חכם chacham to either choose to emphasize the assumptions of the
נודר noder or the language and the words that came out of
the נודר's noder mouth and they could go either way. Oh yes
but but that's certainly true but that is stuff we talked about
like a month ago.
הולכים אחר לשון בני אדם. holchin achar leshon bnei adam. Right? And
how much is it if you remember there was a discussion
about סתם להחמיר פירושם להקל. stam leha'achmir perusham lehakeil. It's sort of
interpreting your scope based on what you were thinking and so on.
So I'm bringing that in, that's not directly what's going on in
the משנה, mishnah, I'm just reminding us of that. Right? But it
does seem to me that that ultimately the חכם chacham has the
authority to draw that line. Yeah I mean the גמרא gemara seems
to try to make distinctions but it always remains pretty fuzzy in
terms of right how much how much do we go by what
he's saying he meant or how much do we go by what
the words actually say. Right? Yeah.
Okay. Okay so so I'm always reminded of a line from from...
Alice in Wonderland, right? What does it say? Something about say what
you mean and mean what you say or something like that. Aren't
those the same thing? No, like
I eat what I see is not the same as I see
what I eat. Okay, okay, חוץ מהאחרונה. Chutz me'hachronah. Anyway, חוץ מהאחרונה,
Chutz me'hachronah, אחרון מותר וכולן אסורין. Acharon mutar vekulan asurin.
So מאן תנא, Man tana, who is this that says that we
say לזה ולזה ולזה ולזה laze u'laze u'laze u'laze that he basically
made a daisy chain? So אמר רבא רבי שמעון היא, Amar Rava
Rabbi Shimon hi, it's רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, דאמר עד שיאמר שבועה
לכל אחד ואחד. d'amar ad sheyomar shevuah l'chol echad v'echad. What the
גמרא Gemara is pointing out
is that the משנה Mishnah goes from saying what's a case where
they're independent? They're independent when you say קונם לזה קונם לזה קונם
לזה קונם לזה, Konam laze, konam laze, konam laze, konam laze, that
makes them independent. So that means the גמרא Gemara is interpreting it
that anything less than using the word קונם Konam makes them linked.
So here's the question: what if I didn't have the conjunctive ו?
vav? What if I said קונם לזה, לזה, לזה, לזה? Konam laze,
laze, laze, laze? Does the ו vav make them linked or not?
Or do I need the ו vav to make them linked? So
the גמרא Gemara says since the משנה Mishnah used the word קונם
Konam for the case of them being independent, it means that anything
less than using that
technical word,
קונם, Konam, קרבן, Korban, נדר, Neder, etc., would mean that they would
be linked, even without the ו. vav. So לזה לזה לזה לזה,
laze laze laze laze, they would also be linked. So how is
this tied into רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? Because the גמרא Gemara has
a similar discussion about a שבועה. Shevuah. If somebody is making a
false שבועה Shevuah and has to bring a קרבן, Korban, how many
שבועות Shevuot did you make? All six of you come and say
to me, where's the 20 bucks you lent me? Each of you
lent me 20 bucks on a different day, and I basically take
a שבועה Shevuah that I don't owe any of you money anymore,
or this would actually in most cases the case of שבועת הפיקדון.
Shevuat hapikadon. You all let me watch your Ferraris, and I take
a שבועה Shevuah that I don't know what you're talking about, and
then it turns out that I lied. So is it one קרבן
Korban or six קרבנות? Korbanot? So if I say שבועה Shevuah that
I don't have anything of any of yours, that's one קרבן. Korban.
But if I say שבועה Shevuah I don't have anything of yours,
and שבועה Shevuah I don't have anything of yours, and שבועה, Shevuah,
six קרבנות. Korbanot. Let's say I say שבועה Shevuah I don't have
anything of yours or yours or yours or yours, is that one
or six? So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says in that case, whether
you use a ו vav or don't use a ו, vav, they
actually are all one until you say שבועה Shevuah to you and
שבועה Shevuah to you and שבועה Shevuah to you, you need that
use of the word שבועה Shevuah to make them independent. So it's
רבי שמעון עד שיאמר שבועה לכל אחד ואחד. Rabbi Shimon ad sheyomar
shevuah l'chol echad v'echad. וחכמים V'chachamim disagree, say that if you say
לזה לזה לזה laze laze laze without the ו, vav, that's enough
to make them independent. Okay.
קונם יין שאני טועם. Konam yayin she'ani to'em. So the משנה Mishnah
says they told him, but old wine is good for digestion. טפי
גבי דאין רע, Tipei gabei d'ein ra, they didn't have to say
it was good for digestion, they just had to say it's not
bad for digestion, right? So why did it have to say it's
good? Alright, whatever. So אמר רבי אבא ועוד יפה קתני. Amar Rabbi
Abba v'od yafeh katani. You're right, it's enough to do a היתר
Heter of the נדר Neder just to say it's not bad for
digestion. I want to drink wine not because I care about my
digestion, I just want it to not be bad. So anyway, it's
enough to say it's not bad, but the משנה Mishnah throws in,
not only is it not bad, it's even good. All right, but
the point is that to make the היתר Heter for the נדר,
Neder, it does not have to be good, it just has to
be not bad. קונם בשר שאני טועם. Konam basar she'ani to'em. And
then they said, oh, but התקופרין hatukufrin is good. טפי גבי דאין
רע. Tipei gabei d'ein ra. You don't need this התקופרין hatukufrin to
be good, you just need it to not be bad. All right,
אמר רבי אבא ועוד יפה קתני. Amar Rabbi Abba v'od yafeh katani.
Okay, fine, for the היתר Heter of the נדר Neder it's enough
to say it's not bad, but they say not only is it
not bad, it's actually even good. Okay, let's take a look at
the משנה. Mishnah. פותחין לאדם בכבוד עצמו ובכבוד בניו. Potchin l'adam bichvod
atzmo uvichvod banav.
So
you also use as a פתח petach his own honor and the
honor of his kids. אומרים לו, Omrim lo, אילו היית יודע. ilu
hayita yode'a. Is that רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar also? Well, no, this
looks like
everybody. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar was the one that said, I understand.
Let's take a look. אילו היית יודע שלמחר אומרים עליך כך היא
וסתו של פלוני. Ilu hayita yode'a she'lemachar omrim alecha kach hi vesto
shel ploni.
This is the person's custom, practice, מגורשת אשתו, megoreshet ishto, and
he just divorced his wife. So by the way, it's very interesting
and ironic that the word וסת, veset, which is used most frequently
in the גמרא Gemara in the context of a woman's cycle, menstrual
cycle, and determining when she is expecting to become a נידה niddah
so husband and wife can't have sex at that time, but וסת
veset just means sort of like habituation, practice, custom,
something that occurs regularly. All right, so it's interesting in the context
of him divorcing his wife, it's using the word וסתו. vesto. Okay,
so anyway, this is your וסת, veset, what do you do? You
just divorced her, because it's assuming that the classic נדר Neder is
between husband and wife and that he says you're not getting any
הנאה hana'ah from me and then it forces him to divorce her,
right? The נדר Neder we've seen that before, that that allowed for
a פתח petach of the כתובה. ketubah. So let's say the guy
says, yeah, I don't care, I have enough money to pay the
כתובה. ketubah. So they'll say, fine, so that's not going to stop.
I would have made the נדר Neder even knowing that I would
have had to pay the כתובה. ketubah. Ah, but would you have
made the נדר Neder knowing that it's going to be hard for
you to get remarried, that everybody's going to be... go around and
saying, watch out for that guy, he makes נדרים nedarim out of
his wazoo and then they wind up being divorced, I wouldn't marry
him, would you have done it then? Okay, so you
talk to and so that's the issue of כבוד עצמו. kovod atzmo.
How does this reflect on you? Okay, that's number one. How about
כבוד בניו? kovod banav? ועל בנותיך ve'al bnosecha you say, and for
your daughters they'll say בנות גרושות הן. bnos grushos hein. So you've
divorced your wife, so now did you realize that that's going to
impact your daughters' shidduch-ability? Already in the times of the משנה Mishnah
they were worried about how these things would impact shidduch-ability. Okay, how
it would impact your daughters' shidduch-ability? Well I mean sadly we know
now, in the חרדי Chareidi community people are very wary of children
of divorce regardless, right? And the משנה Mishnah very concretely spells out
מה ראה אמא של אלו להתגרש, mah ra'ah ima shel elu lehisgareish,
what was it
that led for their mother to be divorced? Maybe they won't know
of the נדר, neder, they'll just see that the mother was divorced
and they'll think it must be that she maybe had bad practices,
or maybe she's some maybe
she committed adultery, or maybe just in general she did not have,
she was not a good wife, and maybe therefore her daughters learned
from her. So I would be wary of this woman's daughters, she's
a divorcee. It's a very sad commentary, right? When a woman gets
divorced it immediately is going to be a great challenge for the
daughters to get... and the משנה Mishnah isn't creating this reality, it's
reflecting this reality, right? So anyway,
so are you sure you would have made your נדר neder if
you would have thought about that implication? ואמר אלו הייתי יודע שכן
לא הייתי נודר, ve'amar ilu hayiti yodei'a shekein lo hayiti noder, if
I had thought about that I wouldn't have made a נדר, neder,
הרי זה מותר, harei zeh mutar, permissible. Let's just finish here. קונם
שאני נושא פלונית כעורה, konam she'ani nosei plonis ke'urah, we've seen this
before, it was quoted yesterday. קונם konam that I won't marry so-and-so
because she's ugly, this ugly woman here, והרי היא נאה ve'harei hi
na'ah and turns out that she's beautiful, I didn't realize. שחורה והרי
היא לבנה sh'chorah ve'harei hi levanah or I thought because she was
dark-skinned turned out she was light-skinned.
קצרה והרי היא ארוכה ktzarah ve'harei hi arucha I thought she was
short, I said this short woman. Okay, it hasn't been sort of
like clear, although it's interesting, maybe it didn't have to be clear,
the דיין dayan will inquire about that. Why did you say this?
Oh, because I thought she was
short. Oh, well did you realize she really wasn't? Oh no, she
was sitting down, right? So in those cases מותר, mutar, but it's
permitted. Now here, the reason it's important that he said the word
though is you don't even really need a היתר heter in this
case because לא מפני שכעורה ונעשית נאה, lo mipnei sheke'urah vena'aseis na'ah,
it's not because circumstances changed, right, that would be a case of
נולד, nolad, שחורה ונעשית לבנה sh'chorah vena'aseis levanah or she was dark-skinned
and became light-skinned, קצרה ונעשית ארוכה ktzarah vena'aseis arucha she was short
and somehow became tall, I don't know how that happened, maybe she
grew up, she was a ten-year-old, I thought she was going to
be that height her whole life. אלא שהנדר
טעות ella she'haneder ta'us because it's fundamentally an error, it was based
on false assumption. Okay, and therefore, right, you don't even presumably need
a היתר. heter. It's not like had you thought through about what
would be the following implications. It's like you fundamentally it was based
on wrong facts, so you don't even really need a היתר heter
fundamentally it's just טעות. ta'us. Okay, ומעשה באחד שנדר מבת אחותו הנאה,
uma'aseh b'echad shenadar mibat achoso hana'ah, a certain person took a נדר
neder from his niece, there was a practice people encouraged to marry
their nieces, men. והכניסוהו vehichnisuhu so he said I'm not going to
get any, she's forbidden to me in הנאה, hana'ah, so we saw
that sort of story before, it was a way of him getting
out of having to be pressured to marry her. Okay, והכניסוה לבית
רבי ישמעאל vehichnisua leveit Rabi Yishmael so they brought her into the
house of Rabi Yishmael, ופיאוה veipeioha and they beautified her. אמר לו
רבי ישמעאל, amar lo Rabi Yishmael, Rabi Yishmael said to him, בני
מזו נדרת? beni mizu nadarta? Did you make a נדר neder about
this woman? ואמר לו לאו, ve'amar lo lav, no, that's a beautiful
woman, I would have never made a נדר neder about her. Okay,
והתירה רבי ישמעאל ve'hitirah Rabi Yishmael and Rabi Yishmael permitted her. באותה
שעה בכה רבי ישמעאל ואמר, ba'osah sha'ah bacha Rabi Yishmael ve'amar, in
that moment Rabi Yishmael cried and said, בנות ישראל נאות הן, bnos
Yisrael na'os hein, daughters of Israel are beautiful, אלא שהעניות מנוולתן ella
she'ha'aniyus menaveltan but the poverty makes them ugly, right, they're underfed, undernourished,
they don't bathe, etc. וכשמת רבי ישמעאל היו בנות ישראל מקוננות קינה
u'keshemais Rabi Yishmael hayu bnos Yisrael mekonenis kinah or
when Rabi Yishmael died, all of the women would have a wailing
and a קינה, kinah, right, it was like a liturgical poetry type,
you know, of wailing that was done as a
lamentation, that's what it was, you know, yeah. ואומרו ve'omro yes, obviously
he took an interest in their welfare. בנות ישראל על רבי ישמעאל
בכינה bnos Yisrael al Rabi Yishmael bechainah and this is what they
said in their lamentation: oh daughters of Israel for
Rabi Yishmael raise up your voice and lament. וכן הוא אומר בשאול
vechein hu omer beShaul and
this is based on the verse in שאול, Shaul, בנות ישראל על
שאול בכינה. bnos Yisrael al Shaul bechainah. Okay, so therefore, anyway, so
it's a lovely story. Now the question here is, was this נולד
nolad or not? Meaning I would read the משנה Mishnah and I'd
read it like, but she really is beautiful, he just had to
clean her up, take a shower, put on some nice clothes, get
a haircut, it's one of those what is it the was the
first makeover reality show.
Anyway, so in that case, it wouldn't be a problem of נולד,
nolad, it's just that he wasn't aware. Okay, let's take a look.
But the גמרא Gemara actually treats it as a נולד nolad case.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says,
let me just finish this off: מעשה לסתור? maiseh listor? It's a
contradiction! Because here it says she made her beautiful. The משנה Mishnah
started by saying that it's not that she became beautiful, that would
have been a נולד nolad situation. Except the משנה... Mishnah... we're only
talking, said the משנה, Mishnah, in case she was already beautiful. Well
this, says the גמרא, Gemara, sounds like even if she became beautiful,
it's worth it. So the גמרא Gemara says חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני.
chisorei mechsara vehachi katan. There's missing words and here's how you have
to read it. רבי ישמעאל אומר, Rabbi Yishmael omer, אפילו כעורה ונעשית
נאה שכעורה ונעשית לבתר כן כעורה ונעשית אבי חתה. afilu ke'ura venasit
na'eh, sheke'ar venasit levatach, ke'ar venasit avuchatech. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael disagrees
and says it's not only that you're
relieved if she was beautiful at the time of the vow, even
if she became beautiful later.
So the... you know, maybe he's not concerned like... like whoever was
that wasn't concerned about נולד. nolad. So, who was it that said
פותחין בנולד? poschin benolad? רבי
מאיר? Rabbi Meir? Not רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Does anybody remember? רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, I think רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So he's like
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Even if it's something that happened in the
future that maybe you couldn't have expected. Nobody was going to expect
that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael was going to do a makeover on
her and she was going to turn out to be beautiful. Okay,
nevertheless for רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, that you can still do a
פתח pesach even בנולד. benolad. I don't know, it was for the
short person too, but okay. The point is רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
goes, I guess, against... מעשה דאחד maiseh de'echad and not אבי חתה,
avuchatech, מעשה דאחד שנדר מבת אחותו והוא maiseh de'echad she'anash bet bito
vahu and he made her beautiful. I know I keep on voicing,
but I'm going to still say this part. But here we're going
to see why the גמרא Gemara interpreted as a נולד nolad rather
than how I would have interpreted that he uncovered her, you know,
her inner beauty, her inner beauty. Okay, but here's going to be
clear what the יפויה iphua is. תנא, Tana, שן של חבש היתה
לה, shen shel cheves hayta lah, she had a type of a,
like of a... of a replacement tooth, no, a replacement tooth. עשה
לה רבי ישמעאל שן של זהב aseh lah Rabbi Yishmael shen shel
zahav and he made it a gold tooth. So one imagines that
the replacement tooth that they had at those times was not natural.
Right, wooden maybe or something. He made it gold and
she became... and at that she became beautiful. Oh really, that was
it? That's all it took?
Okay. כשמת רבי ישמעאל, kshemeis Rabbi Yishmael, when רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
died, פתח עליה ההוא ספדנא, patah ala hahu saftana, the eulogizer opened
up on him and said, הכי: hachi: בנות ישראל על רבי ישמעאל
בכינה, bnot Yisrael al Rabbi Yishmael bechina, daughters of Israel for רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael weep... actually here it's interesting, it seems like the
male eulogizer was saying this rather than the women themselves saying it.
Anyway, so daughters of Israel, raise up a lamentation,
המלבישכם וכולי, hamalbishachem vechulei, he who dressed you רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael,
who dressed you and then וכולי. vechulei. I must say can you
tell me the end? What's the end? The גמרא Gemara doesn't give
you the end. Yes, Michael. Wait, what is it? Just a grammatic
thing, I think it's... I don't think it's בחינה, bechina, it's בכינה
bechina because it was the... used with the כ. kaf. That was
the word I was going to ask about too, בכה. bana.
Oh, I'm sorry. בכינה, bechina, wailing... they opened in the crying. בכינה.
bechina. No, בכינה bechina as in, you know, but just before it
said היו בנות ישראל נושאות קינה. hayu bnot Yisrael nesos kina. Right,
קינה. kina. So I was reading that... I was reading that as
a... as a different spelling but I think you're right, בחינה. bechina.
All right, all right, they were crying. Thank you, thank you. Right,
okay.
The other thing was what I'm trying to understand is, you know,
we have a whole thing about before at the very beginning of
the פרק. perek. We could only be with one
life. No, we'd be with one life, right? Then רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer was saying פוסקין לאדם בכבוד אביו ואמו, poskin leadam bichvod aviv
veimo, and then רבי צדוק Rabbi Zadok was the one who says
היו בכבוד המקום... hayu bichvod hamakom... then there's no need for any...
Right. So wouldn't רבי צדוק Rabbi Zadok have agreed with this too?
If you can do בכבוד עצמו, bichvod atzmo, oh, you just have
to be with yourself. Yes, exactly. In any case, אין הכי נמי,
ein hachi nami,
but it's similar to the case before also we said, had you
realized that, you know, מה שכתוב בתורה, ma shekasuv batorah, had you
realized that you were, you know, that you were being עובר על
לא תשא את שם ה' אלהיך לשוא over al lo sissah es
shem Hashem elokecha lashav and being עובר over on this and being
עובר over on that? First of all, this isn't any case, this
is a case specifically between husband and wife. It's not universal. And
that's why I opened today by saying that part of the חידוש
chidush in these משניות Mishnayos is that you might think that some
of these cases aren't as bad as אביו ואמו, aviv veimo, are
too universal or are too weighty that a person
would... would not fully be honest about them. And that's the חידוש
chidush in the משנה, Mishnah, that they're not as universal or as
weighty as the case of כבוד אביו ואמו. kvod aviv veimo. That's
exactly it. So you'd have a certain problem with that, but not
this. Exactly, exactly. Yeah. Always takes us a step post. What do
we see as the initiate of this? Because if somebody comes to
the בית דין Beis Din and says I took this vow and
now I regret it, yeah, because there's going to be a because
of there. Right. So is פוסקין postin the... No, there's not often
a because. My focus right now is like, it's too hard for
me to keep this vow. That's why most people are, right? So
what we then help you figure out is was that something that
we can figure... was there something at the time you made it
that we can say was in error or not thought... Right now
you're saying it's too hard. Okay, now one of the things we'd
help you realize is have you known, like if I'm going to
say I'm having a really hard time keeping away from smoking cigarettes
and I'm going to say like נדר Neder all cigarettes are forbidden,
okay, and then it's too hard for you, right? Okay, so I
need to be released from my נדר Neder because I need a
cigarette. So could we say, now could we say like, had you
realized, you know, how deep your habit was and how hard it
was, that the נדר Neder would not be enough to make you,
you know, because deep down even though you wanted to get out
of it, but deep down had you realized how dependent you were?
So that would be what we would do. So it could be
that we use your current challenge to say that you weren't thinking
that through at the time. But sometimes, you know, no, at the
time I knew it was going to be really, really, really hard
and you know, and I knew how deep my dependence was and
I still wanted to make the נדר Neder because I wanted to
use it as a way to free me from this. But okay,
I say, you know, so that it's a little harder, right? So
but the reason a person comes to בית דין Beis Din is
not because I wasn't thinking through something then. The reason the person
comes to בית דין Beis Din is like I don't want to
be able to be bound by it right now. The question is,
is this implying perhaps that בית דין Beis Din is going out,
seeking out people who are making נדרים Nedarim and proposing to them
that maybe this wasn't such a good idea? I don't think so,
you mean because פותחין Poschin sounds proactive? It doesn't say מי שבא
לבית דין Mi sheba l'Beis Din or whatever, it just starts with
פותחין. Poschin. I don't know, it's an interesting point. You are right
that it sort of makes it, positions them in a more proactive
way. But you know, they did a lot here through the rhetoric
to say about how terrible it is to make נדרים Nedarim and
so on. I don't know if they, you know, got up and
made announcements in shul, like because you know, anybody who has, who
made a נדר Neder and it was an issue of come see
us, because then it would
be I think the problem that we saw before, because it's too
easy and too universal that it undercuts itself. Yeah. Was Rabbi Yishmael
in this story of the ten martyrs the one who was beautiful?
Oh, I think so, I think you're right. Yeah, right, about the
focus on beauty and Rabbi Yishmael beautifying the daughter, right, right, Rabbi
Yishmael בן אלישע? ben Elisha? Right, right,
you're right, this is definitely Rabbi Yishmael. That, I think it's Rabbi
Yishmael. Thank you, thank you, thank you.
I have to tell you I'm still struggling with this issue about
if
when it's I didn't realize, what the משנה Mishna says, I didn't
realize that she was beautiful, I thought she was ugly, so you
know, that was like a טעות, Ta'us, right? You didn't need a
היתר, Heiter, right? Your assumption of facts was wrong. So going back
to the case by the, I don't know, by the onions, right?
Oh, I didn't realize that some onions were good for you. Okay,
so why is that a היתר? Heiter? Why isn't that a טעות?
Ta'us?
You know, maybe it is. And then it would be a principle,
I guess that's an important question. If we say היתר נדר שהקצתו
הותר כולו, Heiter neder she'iktzaso hutur kulo, we say that
נדר שהקצתו בטעות כולו בטעות. Neder she'iktzaso beta'us kulo bata'us. Once you're
released from it, whether you're released through a process of התרת נדרים,
Hataras Nedarim, right, or you're released from a process of טעות, Ta'us,
either way presumably that you're released from the whole thing, because it
applies to everything. But it would seem to me the case of
the onions and the wine is a case of טעות, Ta'us, not
really a case of היתר. Heiter. Okay, let's continue in the גמרא.
Gemara. ההוא דאמר
לה לדביתהו, Hu d'amar lah l'ivteih, a man said to his wife,
קונם שאי את נהנית לי עד
שתטעימי תבשילך לרבי יהודה ולרבי שמעון. Konam she'i at nehenis li ad
shetat'imi tavshileich l'Rabbi Yehuda u'l'Rabbi Shimon. So קונם, Konam, you can't have
any benefit from me until you go give a taste of your
stew to Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Shimon. So it's funny because now
we're getting an insight into like real life and how people use
נדרים Nedarim not just in like, you know, in a fit of
spite, but also like, you know, it became like trivialized and used
them as like little ways to get people to do uncomfortable things,
you know, little, so, so, and therefore she would get them to,
who knows, maybe he was saying, "Oh my god, this stew is
so amazing, I bet Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Shimon, even the great
Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Shimon would love this," and she says, "Yeah,
yeah," and he says, "No, I'm going to make a נדר, Neder,
I'm going to force you." I don't know, or maybe he's doing
it out of spite. It's the other way, the stew is so
disgusting, I want you to go to the Beis Medrash and let
them see how bad you are. Right, right, but it is,
that's probably the more likely. Anyway, it's quite fascinating how it became
like little,
you know, games, games is the wrong word, but you know, anyway,
between husband and wife. Okay, so אמרה, Amrah, okay, so wait a
minute, Rabbi Yehuda, Rabbi Yehuda would say fine, whatever, even though this
is some, you know, person I never knew, you know, and some,
you know, some villager or something, normally I wouldn't have anything to
do with him, but I'm going to go and taste it.
אמרה, Amrah, and you know, also maybe, maybe there's two questions. One
is like, you know, you don't imagine that Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi
Shimon go ahead and they go to the houses of every, you
know, of every, you know, אליהו הנביא, Eliyahu HaNavi,
right, right, of every guy and woman in
the village. On the other, the other thing is also maybe he
shares the plain. means it's type of a whole dynamic. Okay, but
nevertheless ויתעצב. v’yit’atzev. Right? Maybe it feels like he's being used and
it's belittling of him, you know, to be playing into this dynamic,
but he went there and he wasn't aloof. אמר קל וחומר מה
לעשות שלום בין איש לאשתו, Amar kal v’chomer ma la’asot shalom bein
ish l’ishto, for the sake of making peace between husband and wife,
אמר דאורייתא שמי שנכתב בקדושה, amar d’Oraita sh’mi shenichtav b’kedusha, my name
which was written in holiness, ימחה על המים המאררים, yimacheh al hamayim
ham’arerim, should be scraped into the bitter waters for the סוטה Sotah
in order to prove that she wasn't an adulteress, בספק, b’safek, and
all that is out of a doubt whether she committed adultery, ואני
על אחת כמה וכמה, v’ani al achat kamma v’chamma, and how much
more so should I be מוחל על כבודי mocheil al kvodi and
go ahead and even though it's some harsh type of a little
struggle between husband and wife, play into it if it'll help the
domestic situation. Right, right, right. Rabbi Shimon, that's an important principle in
הלכה halacha that שלום בית shalom bayit is used as a, you
know, to in certain circumstances to permit things that we normally wouldn't
allow. Rabbi Shimon לא קאים, lo ka’im, Rabbi Shimon refused to play
it, play. אמר ימותו כל בני אלמנה, Amar yamutu kol bnei almana,
let all the sons of this אלמנה almana die. Now, she's not
an אלמנה, almana, so the first thing he's implying is let him
die, let his sons die, I don't care, let 'em all ואל
יזוז שמעון ממקומו. v’al yazuz Shimon mimkomo. I am not, I'm not
moving out of my seat. Okay, so I'm not playing into their
silly game.
ועוד כי היכי V’od ki heichi or something about the word עוד
od because
if we have the word עוד, od, it means number one, this
is beneath my honor, number two, I think that this is a
bad idea, you know, societally and halachically. If you take out the
word ועוד, v’od, it's not about his honor at all, it's about
the halachic concern. What's the halachic concern? כי היכי דלא להתרגלו למינדר,
Ki heichi d’lo lihitraglu limindar, that people should not become accustomed to
what happens? Every time somebody makes a נדר neder in their house,
they can force a great rabbi, oh, but the rabbis have to
do it for the שלום בית shalom bayit and let's, let's say
I'm gonna, you know, נדר neder all my stuff is אסור assur
to me unless you can get the rabbi to play hopscotch or
whatever, you know,
it becomes absurd. So at a certain point you say, we're not
playing any of your stupid games, you know? And I, you know,
you understand that because you just wind up encouraging it. It's like
there's this whole case in the גמרא Gemara that says if somebody
basically,
I think I remember with שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei or שמע. Shema.
I think it was like, I think it was שמע. Shema. If
somebody said שמע Shema and they didn't have כוונה kavanah or something,
like you should say it again. I'm not, anyway, and the other
person said something like, like, what? You're being so casual with God
that you're saying it without כוונה? kavanah? Don't say it again! How
dare you be so casual with God? And you don't say it
again, and I wasn't יוצא, yotzei, and right? So if I wasn't
יוצא, yotzei, I gotta say it again! No, because if we let
you say it again this time, then it's just encouraging in the
future you to not have right כוונה. kavanah. So you know, it's
an interesting lesson. Don't play in, in this situation, it just encourages
them. Yes, Charlie. I was gonna say the same thing. I mean,
if the rabbis sort of put their foot down and refuse to
cooperate with all these people who make frivolous נדרים, nedarim, eventually the
word will get out and people might stop. Right, so that's the
question about why we have התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim altogether. Why don't
we just say you're bound by it and tough luck, and then
people will realize how weighty it is. But it seems that that
wasn't the
problem. It seems the rabbis had like a lot of fixing up
to do. It seemed that the problem was that people made frivolous
נדרים nedarim and then they didn't keep by it either, you know?
So, so the rabbis wanted to say, when you take a נדר,
neder, you really have to keep by it. Oh, but there's all
this frivolous, it's hard to treat it seriously if everybody is saying
like, it's like, you know how some people in some societies, like
people say curse words every third word, right? If people are making
a נדר neder every third word, it's hard for them to take
it seriously. So the rabbis had a lot of work to do.
They said, look, there's true, a lot of נדרים nedarim aren't really
binding, here's the way you get out of them, but the ones
that are real are really real and you have to treat them
seriously, right? So that was hard to try to change those, those
practices in society. I, I want to understand, this סוגיא sugya is
a fantastic, this מעשה, ma'aseh,
educationally. In other words, is the role of the rabbi to assert
the authority of הלכה halacha or is it to be pastorally involved
in the lives of the people? Right, it's a phenomenal case. Right,
thank you. Yup. So now there's a case just like it. ההוא
דאמר לה לדביתיה, Hahu d’amar lah l’dviteih, a man said to his
wife, קונם שכי נהנית לי עד שתרוקי בו ברבי שמעון בן גמליאל,
konam shechi nehenit li ad shetaroki bo b’Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel, you
have to spit at Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel. Okay,
so you could imagine, I don't know why he would be doing
this, again, maybe just to make his wife miserable, maybe he didn't
like Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel, but he didn't want to be the
one to spit at him. So,
אתת, atat, she came, ורקקה אלבושיה, v’rakaka alvushiah, she spat on his
garment, on his clothes, not in his face, but you know, in,
in his shirt. אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא, Amar leih Rav
Acha miDifti l’Ravina, some have the גרסא, girsa, if you look down
at the חית, chet, some have the גרסא girsa בשריא, bishraya, and
then she, and I don't know who the one who was permitted
it, but somebody permitted her. So maybe it was even
Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel. Anyway, אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא amar
leih Rav Acha miDifti l’Ravina So somebody said it was permitted. Okay,
it's clear from the context that somebody said it was permitted. אמר
ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא, Amar lei Rav Acha Midifti l'Ravina, so
Rav Acha from Diphti said to Ravina, בהאי זילותא קמכוין, bahay ziluta
kamichavein,
he was trying to, you know, disgrace Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel,
and that wasn't, and therefore he didn't want it to be at
him himself, not just his clothes, so the condition wasn't satisfied. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so Ravina said back, מי רגלי מנא דרבן שמעון
בן גמליאל זילותא רבתא היא. mei raglei mana d'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
ziluta rabta hee. No,
even spitting on his clothes is a tremendous, you know, disgraceful thing
and therefore that is considered within him. Let's hear a bit more.
But Ravina lived a couple hundred years after Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel.
Right, so they're reflecting on the story, they weren't there at the
story. But yes, the understanding is that the husbands in these little
scenarios are saying no sex until you do the following. Yeah, not
just sex, food,
anything, right. Like a הנאה hana'ah in the larger, like I'm on
strike. Exactly, a husband on strike. Exactly. And the wife in theory
could do the same, you know? This has been suggested as a
solution to the agunah problem. Yeah. אמר ליה, Amar lei, okay so,
okay let's keep going. ההוא דאמר לה לדביתהו, Hahu d'amar lah l'devithu,
a certain man said to his wife, קונם שאי את נהנית לי
עד שתראי מאום, Konam she-ee at nehenit lee ad she-tirei me'um, but
the text says מאום, me'um, but everybody says it's מאום ma'um like
מאומה, me'uma, so anything, יפה שבי לבי רבי ישמעאל. yafeh she-bi l'bei
Rabbi Yishmael.
You can't get benefit from me until you show something that's beautiful
in you to Rabbi Yishmael ברבי יוסי. berabi Yose. You're so ugly
and disgusting and whatever,
so unless you can find something beautiful about you to show to
Rabbi Yishmael ברבי יוסי, berabi Yose, you'll be forbidden to me. So
אמר להם, amar lahem, so Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi
Yose said to them, presumably the students or whoever it was that
told him about the case, שמא ראשה נאה, Shema roshah na'eh, maybe
she's got a beautiful head. אמרו לו סגלגל, Amru lo sigalgal,
no it's very spherical, it doesn't look nice. שמא שערה נאה, Shema
se'arah na'eh, maybe she has beautiful
hair. דומה לאניצי פשתן, Domeh l'anitzei pishtan, it's like flax.
I don't know, isn't that usually a nice compliment, flaxen hair? But
that's about the color, right? No, this means it's all dried out.
I
know the meaning, though, I know, I have a hard time reading
this, this is a really long, entire thing, this is bad. Yeah,
we need women in the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. What? בית מדרש.
Beis Medrash. Yeah, but let me give you the scoop. שמא עיניה
נאות, Shema eyneha na'ot, maybe she has beautiful eyes. טרוטות, Trutot, no
they're
circular. Okay, like big
circles. I guess it's all like taste anyway, but that was assumed
to be objectively not a good look. שמא אזניה נאות, Shema ozneha
na'ot, maybe she has beautiful ears. כפולות, Kfulot, no they're like folded
over, they're flappy. שמא חוטמה נאה, Shema chotmah na'eh, maybe she has
a beautiful nose. בלום, Blum, no it's clogged up or something, I
don't know, it's like a ball. שמא שפתותיה נאות, Shema siftoteha na'ot,
maybe she has beautiful lips. עבות, Avot, they're thick. I don't know,
nowadays people think that that's very attractive. שמא צוארה נאה, Shema tzavarah
na'eh, maybe she has a beautiful neck. שקוט, Shakut, no it's very
short. שמא כריסה נאה, Shema krisah na'eh, maybe she has a beautiful
tummy. צבה, Tzavah, no it's bloated.
שמא רגליה נאות, Shema ragleha na'ot, maybe her legs. רחבות כשל אווזא,
Rachavot k'shel avza, no they're as wide as a duck. I don't
know, do ducks have big legs?
It is the feet. Ah, feet, ah, okay.
Webbed feet.
Okay, fine. שמא שמה נאה, Shema shmah na'eh,
maybe her name is beautiful. לכלוכית, Lichluchit, her name is like disgusting,
trash, dirt. Her name is dirt.
So he said, אמר להם, amar lahem, oh! Oh! He said, oh
that's her name? יפה קורין אותה לכלוכית שהיא מלוכלכת במומין. Yafeh korin
otah Lichluchit she-hee meluchlechet b'mumin. It's beautiful that they call her
Lichluchit because she is all, you know,
dirty with all these blemishes. ושריא, V'sharyah, and he permitted her. He
permitted her because that was what was beautiful about her. It was
so beautiful that
her name fit who she was. That's the key, the key word
here is יפה. yafeh. יפה קורין אותה לכלוכית. Yafeh korin otah Lichluchit.
Oh, that's what's beautiful about her. Very brilliant. Okay, anyway, I mean
it's very sexist, here it's emphasis, but it's still brilliant. You know
what's interesting, though, I remember about that story, wasn't there like even
a Jesus story, like he was going down the road with somebody,
right, and then, oh how nice... yeah,
yeah, about an eye, what beautiful... No, no, but the guy said,
oh it means like whatever, and he was thinking about the eyes,
what beautiful, but it said, oh it's rotten, and he's doing exactly
that. Well, he's not looking at her, he's asking other people, but
he's also doing it to look at her, I understand.
But
the גמרא Gemara says that's allowed for a purpose. Right, that's a
good point. Right, that's a good point. Like, right, if it, you
don't have to interpret it just physically, because her name is fitting
to who she is. Why did they explore her מדות middot and
her character and other things? Right, so that is also very troubling.
It's very commodifying of the woman. I don't know, it's a good
question. I do want to say that some ראשונים, Rishonim, some ראשונים,
Rishonim, I do think
that obviously the whole point to this is how brilliant it was
that he got the word יפה yafe out of this whole situation,
but some ראשונים Rishonim don't read it that way. Like the
ר"ן Ran reads it like there was nothing beautiful about her and
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael permitted her. Why? Because he says because even
though the guy says, "you're forbidden until רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael finds
something beautiful," what he meant was he was just trying to prove
to his wife, thank you very much, that there was nothing as
beautiful and attractive about her. So once that had been proven through
this process, obviously then he meant for the נדר neder not to
be binding. He meant for her to go through the process, not
necessarily to discover something beautiful, but he wanted to force her to
go through the process. That's how the ר"ן Ran reads it. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara finishes the following way. Okay, ההוא
בר בבל. Ahu Bar Bavel. Now this is a גמרא Gemara that
is also like about language and understanding and husband and wife, whatever,
but this is a nice little piece of גמרא Gemara you'll hear
that is like about, I know somebody who uses this piece of
גמרא Gemara like when he's preparing couples to be married, about the
importance, about how people, about communication issues, that sometimes somebody says one
thing and something very different is heard. So let's take a look.
Okay, ההוא בר בבל, Ahu Bar Bavel, now let's see. דסליק לארץ
ישראל, De'salik l'Eretz Yisrael, he went to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael where
they spoke a Palestinian Aramaic
and he spoke a Babylonian Aramaic. Okay? So they thought
that they were speaking the same common... what was it Churchill said
about England and the United States, separated by a common language? Yeah,
so they thought they were speaking the same language, but they meant
very different things by what they were saying. So, נסב אתתא, nassa
itta, he married a woman. אמר לה, Amar lah, he says to
her, בשלי לי תרי טלפי, basheli li trei talsi, cook for me
two.
Now the way, again, different interpretations, could be like hoofs, he meant
like two nice like legs of an animal, okay? בשלה ליה תרי
טלפחי Bashela lei trei talafchi is
again this version. Fine, she cooked for him two lentil beans. So
can mean like hoofs of an animal or it can mean lentil
beans, so she cooked two lentils. Some say that what happened was
that he said "two" as a way of speaking, which just meant
like "some". You know, make me some, make me some. So she
made her some, she made him two.
Okay, fine. So רתח עלה, ratah alah, he got angry. Misunderstood it.
למחר, L'machar, אמר לה, amar lah, בשלי לי גריוא. basheli li garriva.
Fine, that's what, you know, you made me just
two, now make me like a whole, you know, make me a
ton. בשלה ליה גריוא, Bashla lei garriva, so she literally made him
a ton. She made him exactly what he said. Okay, so he
was getting pretty fed up.
אמר לה, Amar lah, זילי אייתי לי תרי בוציני, zili ayiti li
trei butzini, go get me two. So now can mean a melon,
but in... also, אייתי ליה תרי שרגי, ayita lei trei shargi, so
it could also mean... a בוצינא butzina could also be a light,
a lamp. She brought him two candles. Okay, so again, in one
type of Aramaic it means melon and the other means candles, and
so also among you have these a million and a billion jokes.
Right? Did anybody ever read that? Anyway, all right. So... שרגי. shargi.
אמר לה, Amar lah, זילי תברינהו על
רישא דבבא, zili tavi ayinhu al reisha d'Baba,
he got so fed up with her, he said, "go break it
on the top of the door," right? בבא Baba is like the
gate or the door. Okay? הוה יתיב בבא בן בוטא Havai yativ
Baba ben Buta was sitting אבבא ad'baba by the door. Okay? So
בבא Baba was by the בבא. baba. So there is this very
comic which is בבא, Baba, right? So anyway, וקא דיין דינא v'ka
dan dina and he was in the middle of a court case.
אזלה ותברתהו
על רישיה, Azla v'tavinhu al reishei, she broke it on his head,
which is likely why this was brought in, because rabbis be pulled
into these little domestic disputes. Okay? אמר לה, Amar lah, says to
her, מה דאיתא עבדת, mah deita avat, what is it that you
did? You broke a melon on my head? Actually, it wasn't a
melon, it was a candle or something, right? Because she brought the
candles instead of the melon. Anyway, אמר ליה, amar lei, she said
to him, כך צוני בעלי, kach tzivani ba'ali, that's what my husband
commanded me. אמר, Amar, says, עשית רצון בעליך, asit retzon ba'alech, you
did the desire of your husband, which is the whole irony that
she didn't do the desire of her husband, she did what she
heard her husband say. No, that's true, the whole thing is about
interpretation. המקום יוציא ממך שני בנים כבבא בן בוטא, HaMakom yotzi mimcha
shenei vanim k'Baba ben Buta, you should merit two sons like בבא
בן בוטא. Baba ben Buta. הדרן עלך המדיר, Hadran alach HaMa'adir, so
it is very beautiful because, right, as both of you were saying,
one was saying, right, the whole part of all of מסכת נדרים
Masechet Nedarim is interpreting what the language means, right, and he is
hearing it and so on, right, but the other part is like,
you know. Is that I think it’s that he’s like, how do
you really know what somebody means? Yeah, and I think that the
fact that he’s sort of that בבא Bava is like reframing it.
Like he could have gotten very upset. No, but besides that he
could have gotten upset, but he’s sort of, he’s trying to sort
of say, look, there’s a lot of miscommunication going on here, but
everybody’s trying to do the right thing, right? So like, you know,
that’s a very healthy thing. So he’s saying, he’s reframing it as
you did what he, what he, you did what your husband wanted.
And she did do what the husband wanted, technically, ironically, but you
were trying to do what he wanted, right? So it’s like reframing.
Look, look, look, it seems to me there’s a lot of things
going on here, but everybody’s intention is in the right place. So
let’s just work on communication. Okay, so this bit of pastoral counseling
גמרא. Gemara. All right, so we will end with that. Such things
really do form a פתח petach actually.
You tried to do what you understood your husband wanted you to
do. Right. And had you understood...